28 chapter 29 of Black Beauty this LibriVox recording is in the public
domain Black Beauty by Anna suul chapter 29 Cockney Then there is the steam engine style of
driving; these drivers were mostly people from towns, who never had a horse of
their own and generally traveled by rail.
They always seem to think that a horse was something like a steam engine only
smaller. At any rate, they think that if only they pay for it a horse is bound to
go just as far and just as fast and with
just as heavy a load as they please. And be the roads heavy and muddy, or dry and
good; be they stony or smooth, uphill or downhill, it is all the same— —on, on, on, one
must go, at the same pace, with no relief and no consideration. These people never think
of getting out to walk up a steep hill.
Oh, no, they have paid to ride, and ride they will! The horse? Oh, he's used to it!
What were horses made for, if not to drag people uphill? Walk! A good joke
indeed! And so the whip is PED and the rain is chucked and often a rough,
scolding voice cries out, “Go along, you lazy beast!” And then another slash of the whip,
when all the time we are doing our very best to get along, uncomplaining and
obedient, though often sorely harassed and downhearted This steam engine style of
driving wears us up faster than any other kind. I would far rather go 20
miles with a good considerate driver than I would go 10 with some of these; it
would take less out of me. Another thing, they scarcely ever put
on the break however steep the downhill may be, and thus bad accidents sometimes
happen; or if they do put it on, they often forget to take it off at the
bottom of the hill, and more than once I have had to pull halfway up the next
hill, with one of the wheels held by the brake, before my driver chose to think
about it; and that is a terrible strain on a horse. Then these Cockys instead of
starting at an easy pace, as a gentleman would do, generally set off at full speed
from the very stable yard and when they want to stop, they first whip us then
pull up so suddenly that we are nearly thrown on our hunches and our mouths
jagged with the bit— —they call that pulling up with a dash; and when they
turn a corner they do it as sharply as if there were no right side or wrong
side of the road. I will remember one spring evening
I and Rory had been out for the day. (Rory was the horse that mostly went with me
when a pair was ordered, and a good honest fellow he
was.) We had our own driver, and as he was always considerate and gentle with us, we
had a very pleasant day. We were coming home at a good smart pace, about twilight.
Our road turned sharp to the left; but as we were close to the hedge on our own
side, and there was plenty of room to pass, our driver did not pull us in. As we
neared the corner I heard a horse and two wheels coming rapidly down the hill
toward us. The hedge was high, and I could see nothing, but the next moment we were
upon each other. Happily for me, I was on the side
next the hedge. Rory was on the left side
of the pole, and had not even a shaft to protect him. The man who was driving was
making straight for the corner, and when he came in sight of us he had no time to
pull over to his own side. The whole shock came upon
Rory. The gig shaft ran right into the chest, making him stagger back with a cry
that I shall never forget. The other horse was thrown upon his haunches and one shaft
broken. It turned out that it was a horse from our own stables, with the high-
wield gig that the young men were so fond of. The driver was one of those random,
ignorant fellows, who don't even know which is their own side of the road, or,
if they know, don't care. And there was poor Rory with his flesh torn open and
bleeding, and the blood streaming down. They said if it had been a little
more to one side it would have killed him; and a good thing for him, poor fellow,
if it had. As it was, it was a long time
before the wound healed, and then he was sold for coal carting and what that is,
up and down those steep hills, only horses know. Some of the sights I saw there,
where a horse had to come downhill with a heavily loaded two wheel cart behind
him, on which no break could be placed, make me sad even now to think of.
After Rory was disabled I often went in the carriage with a M named Peggy, who
stood in the next stall to mine. She was a strong, well-made animal, of a bright
dun color, beautifully dappled, and with a dark brown mane and tail. There was no
high breeding about her, but she was very pretty and remarkably sweet tempered and
willing. Still, there was an anxious look about her eyes by which I knew she had some
trouble. The first time we went out together I thought she had a very odd
pace; she seemed to go partly a trot, partly a caner three or four paces, and
then a little jump forward. It was very unpleasant for any
horse who pulled with her, and made me quite fidgety. When we got home I asked her
what made her go in that odd, awkward way a she said in a troubled manner, “I
know my paces are very bad, but what can
I do? It is really not my fault; it is just because my legs are so short. I
stand nearly as high as you, but your legs are a good 3 Ines longer above your
knee than mine, and of course you can take a much longer step and go much
faster. You see I did not make myself. I wish I could have done so; I would have
had long legs then. All my troubles come from my short legs,” said Peggy, in a desponding
tone. “But how is it,” I said, “when you were so strong and good tempered and
willing?” “Why, you see,” said she, “men will go so fast, and if one can't keep up to
other horses it is nothing but whip, whip, whip, all the time. And so I have had to
keep up as I could, and have got into this ugly shuffling pace. It was not
always so; when I lived with my first master I always went a good regular trot,
but then he was not in such a hurry. He was a young clergyman in the country, and
a good, kind master he was. He had two churches a good way apart, and a great
deal of work, but he never scolded or whipped me for not going faster. He was
very fond of me. I only wish I was with
him now; but he had to leave and go to a
large town, and then I was sold to a farmer. “Some farmers, you know, are capital
masters; but I think this one was a low sort of man. He cared nothing about good
horses or good driving; he only cared for going fast. I went as fast as I could, but
that would not do, and he was always whipping; so I got into this way of
making a bring forward to keep up. On market nights he used to stay very late
at the inn, and then drive home at a gallop. “One dark night he was galloping
home as usual, when all of a sudden the wheel came against some great heavy
thing in the road, and turned the gig over in a minute. He was thrown out and
his arm broken, and some of his ribs, I
think. At any rate, it was the end of my
living with him, and I was not sorry. But you see it will be the same everywhere
for me, if men must go so fast. I wish my legs were
longer!” Poor Peggy! I was very sorry for her, and I could not comfort her, for I
knew how hard it was upon slow paced horses to be put with fast ones; all the
whipping comes to their share, and they can't help it. She was often used in a fighton and
was very much liked by some of the ladies, because she was so gentle; and
sometime after this she was sold to two ladies who drove themselves, and wanted a
safe, good horse.
I met her several times out in the country, going a good steady pace, and
looking as gay and contented as a horse could be. I was very glad to see her, for
she deserved a good place. After she left us another horse
came in herstead He was young, and had a bad name for shying and starting, by
which he had lost a good place. I asked him what made him
shy. “Well, I hardly know,” he said. “I was
timid when I was young I was a good deal frightened several times, and if I saw
anything strange I used to turn and look at it— —you see, with our blinkers one
can't see or understand what a thing is unless one looks around and then my
master always gave me a whipping, which of course made me start on, and did not
make me less afraid. I think if he would have let me
just look at things quietly, and see that there was nothing to hurt me, it would
have been all right, and I should have got used to them. One day say an old
gentleman was riding with him, and a large piece of white paper or rag blew
across just on one side of me. I shied and started forward. My master as usual
whipped me smartly, but the old man cried out, 'You're wrong! you're wrong! You should
never whip a horse for shying; he shies because he is frightened, and you only
frighten him more and make the habit worse.' So I suppose all men don't do so
I'm sure I don't want to shy for the
sake of it; but how did one know what is dangerous and what is not, if one is
never allowed to get used to anything I'm never afraid of what I
know. Now I was brought up on a park where there were deer; of course I knew
them as well as I did a sheep or a cow,
but they are not common, and I know many sensible horses who are frightened at
them, and who kick up quite a shindy before they will pass a paddock where they are
deer.” I knew what my companion said was true, and I wished that every young horse
had as good masters as far MC gry and Squire Gordon. Of course we sometimes come in
for good driving here. I remember one morning I was put into the light gig, and
taken to a house in Pony Street. Two gentlemen came out; the taller of them
came round to my head; he looked at the bit and Bridal and just shifted the
collar with his hand, to see if it fitted comfortably. “Do you consider this horse
wants a curb?” he said to the Hustler Well,” said the man, “I should say
he would go just as well without; he has an uncommon good mouth, and though he has
a fine spirit he has no vice; but we generally find people like the
curb.” “I don't like it,” said the gentleman;
“be so good as to take it off, and put the
rain in at the cheek. An easy mouth is a
great thing on a long journey, is it not, old fellow?” he said, patting my
neck. Then he took the rains and they both got up. I can remember now how
quietly he turned me round, and then with a light feel of the rain and drawing the
whip gently across my back, we were off. I arched my neck and set off at my
best pace. I found I had someone behind me who knew how a good horse ought to be
driven. It seemed like the old times again, and made me feel quite
gay. This gentleman took a great liking to me, and after trying me several times
with the saddle he prevailed upon my master to sell me to a friend of his, who
wanted a safe, pleasant horse for riding.
And so it came to pass that in the summer I was sold to Mr.
Barry end of chapter